<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The interest of England stated: or A faithful and just account of the aims of all parties now pretending. Distinctly treating of the designements of [brace] the Roman Catholick. The royalist. The Presbyterian. The Anabaptist. The Army. The late Protector. The Parliament. With their effects in respect of themselves, of one another, and of the publick. Cleerly evidencing the unavoydable ruine upon all from longer contest: and offering an expedient for the composure of the respective differences; to the security and advantage, not onely of every single interest, but to the bringing solid, lasting peace unto the nation.</title>
            <author>Fell, John, 1625-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E763_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862449</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E763[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The interest of England stated: or A faithful and just account of the aims of all parties now pretending. Distinctly treating of the designements of [brace] the Roman Catholick. The royalist. The Presbyterian. The Anabaptist. The Army. The late Protector. The Parliament. With their effects in respect of themselves, of one another, and of the publick. Cleerly evidencing the unavoydable ruine upon all from longer contest: and offering an expedient for the composure of the respective differences; to the security and advantage, not onely of every single interest, but to the bringing solid, lasting peace unto the nation.</title>
                  <author>Fell, John, 1625-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Fell.</note>
                  <note>The words "The Roman .. Parliament." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 22th [sic]".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114608:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Intereſt of England ſtated:</hi> OR A faithful and juſt Account of the Aims of all Parties now pretending.</p>
            <p>Diſtinctly treating of the Deſignements of
<list>
                  <item>The <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Royaliſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Presbyterian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Anabaptist.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Army.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>late Protector.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With their Effects in reſpect of <hi>themſelves,</hi> of <hi>one another,</hi> and of the <hi>Publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CLEERLY EVIDENCING The unavoydable ruine upon <hi>all</hi> from longer conteſt: AND Offering an <hi>Expedient</hi> for the compoſure of the reſpective Differences; to the <hi>ſecurity</hi> and <hi>advantage,</hi> not onely of every <hi>ſingle intereſt,</hi> but to the bringing ſolid, laſting <hi>Peace</hi> unto the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114608:2"/>
            <head>The Intereſt of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> Stated.</head>
            <p>TO have a thorough ſenſe of our preſent Sufferings, and a certain knowledge of the inevitable ruine, which our diviſions (if not compoſed) will bring upon the Publick; as it is a matter of little difficulty in its ſelf, ſo of very inconſiderable uſe; that which would be more behoveful, were to find out and expedient, for the allevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ills we now feel, and the prevention of thoſe we fear; both of which, having been by ſeveral means during a long tract of time in vain attempted, the caſe is now by many given over as incurable; but upon ſerious Conſideration it appears, that not the Malignancy of our diſeaſe, has occaſioned thoſe miſcarriages, but the ill application of remedies has done it. In particular, that men have not either deſired to know, or to remove the diſtempers of the <hi>Publick,</hi> but laboured to throw off their <hi>Single</hi> and immediate preſſures, and to that end, endevoured to advance the party they adher'd to, and to beat down all others: whereby it came about, that Diviſions in ſtead of Compoſute, have ſtill grown wider; and paſſionate Hates inſtead of being allayed, have riſen higher, and been more exaſperated. But it being certain, that the real good of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſiſts not in the private benefit of ſingle Men, but the advantage of the Publick; and that is made up, not by the Welfare of any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but of all; 'tis evident, that the only means to procure the general good, muſt be commenſurate unto the whole Community; looking upon all perſons, not as Heads or Partiſans of any private faction or Intereſt, but as Members of the Nation; and the pretentions of ſingle Men or parties, however numerous, are only ſo far forth to be purſued, as they advance the other general Intereſt. Which being laid down as evident and certain truth, the next conſideration wil be, what are the Intereſts of all the ſeveral parties of the Nation now on foot, and what the Publick is; that ſo diſcovery may be made how conſiſtent the private aims are, both among themſelves, and with the general: and alſo how poſſible it is to find out an expedient, for the atcheivement of the common good.</p>
            <p>If we take a view of the ſeveral pretentions, carried on in the Nation apart, we ſhall find the moſt conſiderable to be, the <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> the <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Protectorian,</hi> the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114608:3"/>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> aim not only to abrogate the penal Laws, and become capable of all employments in the Common-wealth; but to introduce his religion, to reſtore the rights of the Church, and utterly era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate all that he eſteems Hereſie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> deſire to bring in the King a Conquerour, to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their loſſes in the late War, be rendered capable of civil employment, and have the former Government of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> deſire to ſet up his diſcipline, to have the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant reinforc'd, and only ſuch as take it, to be employed in Church or State; to be indempnified in reference to what they have done, and ſecur'd of what they poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis the Wiſh of the <hi>Baptized Churches,</hi> that there might be no Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Government of any kind, nor Miniſterial function, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for it; and that onely perſons ſo minded, ſhould be capable of employment, likewiſe to be indempnified for what they have done.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis the aim of the <hi>Army,</hi> to govern the Nation, to keep themſelves from being disbanded, or engaged it war, to ſecure their pay, and to be indempnified for all paſt action.</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis the deſire of the Family of the late <hi>Protector</hi> to eſtabliſh the Heir of his Houſe, that they may rule him, and he the Nation, and ſo both preſerve and advance themſelves.</p>
            <p n="7">7. 'Tis the wiſh of the preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> (as far as they have one common deſign) to continue themſelves in abſolute power, by the ſpecious name of a popular Government; to new model and divide, and at laſt, take down the <hi>Army;</hi> and finally under the pretence of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Parliament or Councel of State, ſet up an Oligarchy; reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling that of the thirty Tyrants in <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, 'Tis the general intereſt of the Nation to eſtabliſh the ancient fundamental Laws, upon which every ones propriety and liberty are built, to ſettle Religion, to procure a general Indempnity for all actions paſt, to revive their languiſhing and almoſt dead trade, gain an alliance with our neighbour States; to put the Government in ſuch hands, as beſides preſent force, can plead a legal title to it; into the hands of ſuch with whoſe private intereſt that of the publick not onely conſiſts, but in which 'tis neceſſarily involved; which likewiſe does leaſt contradict the aims of particular parties: Laſtly, the hands of ſuch, whoſe counſel is fit to direct in matters of deliberation, and courage fit to vindicate the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Having impartially propoſed the ſeveral intereſts that each party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to it ſelf, we come now to conſider how far they are attainable; or if attained, how conſiſtent with the publick benefit, next how conſiſtent with that of all other parties reſpectively, and in fine how productive of the real benefit of themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114608:3"/>
            <p>Firſt, as to the Roman Catholick pretenſions of reſtoring to the Pope his ancient revenue and juriſdiction, and the Church all that was alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths time, 'tis no way feizable; the Perquiſites of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the payments to the Pope being greater than our Contributions ſo much complained of, and the impoſſibility of reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Church-Lands is plain from what was done in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, when the greateſt zealots for that profeſſion, choſe rather to throw their Beads into the fire, than reſign their Conveyances of Abby-land; then as to his religion, 'tis viſibly the ruine of all other parties. Q. <hi>Maries</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation by fire and fagot, with all the terrors of the Inquiſition, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſeparable attendants on it: now the bulk of the Nation being poſſeſt of the uſage they ſhould have from the Roman Catholicks, if they prevailed, beſides all other Antipathies deeply radicated in the minds of far the greateſt part of the Nation; it is morally impoſſible it ſhould ever introduct without a forraign force of ſuch ſtrength as to make an abſolute conqueſt; which would involve the whole Nation, and the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in one common ruine. <hi>The ſword not diſtinguiſhing the Catholick from the Heretick;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The very words of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Frier, when demanded what they would do with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholicks in 88.</note> 
               <hi>and having onely this kindneſs for its friends, to ſend them ſpeedily to Heaven, when the other were deſigned for Hell,</hi> and this the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks were ſenſible of in the invaſion of 88, aſſuring the Queen of as great fidelity as they could expect from any of her Proteſtant Subjects.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> pretenſion of having the K. an abſolute Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, as it would deſtroy the intereſt of all parties that have appeared againſt him or his Father, would infringe the the liberties of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects in general, and in fine, oppreſs the Cavaleir himſelf: beſides, is no way attainable by that party, being inconſiderable both in number and warlick pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arations to the reſt: yet farther, ſhould he ſo prevail, the looking back for reſtitution of all damages paſt in ſo many years, were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt his intereſt, and would forfeit the moſt abſolute victory: no power being retained by violence, however acquired thereby. And in thoſe terms of difficulty, the ſetting up the primitive Government of the Church, at leaſt in its full height, againſt ſo great a multitude of eager diffenters, according to probability will not ſtand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> aims of ſetting up his Diſcipline, has the former inconveniences, with the addition of ſome others; for beſides that, its riſe muſt be the overthrow of all other parties, which are more conſiderable in the Nation then themſelves; that rigid Government no ways complies with the <hi>genius</hi> of the Nation, nor the frame of our Municipal Laws: which the late King was well aware of, when he conceded to the ſetting of it up for three years, being fully ſatisfied how effectual an argument the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114608:4"/>experience of that ſhort time would be to perſwade the Nation to endure ſo galling a heavy a yoak no longer; as to the point of Indempnity, and that is ſecured ſufficiently in the preceeding paragraph, for if the <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> who are the great ſufferers muſt have no reparations (as I am confident they expect more) there is no other party elſe to fear the making any, and as the Caſe now ſtands in the Church, the late diſcouragements for learning, have left ſo ſmall a ſtore of perſons fit for Eccleſiaſtical em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, that Livings will want Scholars of what party ſoever, and be ſcarce ſupplied; and not Scholars be deſtitute of Livings.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the pretenſions of the <hi>Baptiſed Churches</hi> have no leſs inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence attending them: as firſt, importing the ruin of all other profeſſions of religion; the adherents to which are evidently not onely the moſt numerous, but infinitely the moſt ſubſtantial part of the Nation; then if attained, cannot poſſibly ſubſiſt, it being a Maxime in policy, that <hi>Religion is the Cement of Government,</hi> without a publick profeſſion of which, and the maintenance of Learning and Miniſtry, Atheiſme and diſorder muſt needs break in: withal, they having a temporal Government, either in a ſingle perſon, or community, to which even themſelves would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animouſly ſubmit, they cannot incorporate into a civil ſociety, of any kind. Laſtly, the practiſes in <hi>Germany</hi> by the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> there; their cruelty, and all manner of diſorder; their taking away all proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Eſtates, founding it in Grace and Saintſhip, with the hard treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> have found, and the <hi>Presbyterian Scots</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> part of the ſame Kingdome have lately received from that party, make all other infinitely diſſatisfied in their acquiring any power over them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, as to the <hi>Armies</hi> governing the Nation; I ſhall not inſiſt on the inconſiderableneſs of their number, or the intolerableneſs of being ruled by the ſword, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there needs no more be ſaid, but that a few weeks ſince they ſo plainly ſaw the impoſſibility of it, that they were content to put the power into the hands of them they had moſt highly diſobliged of all men, and whoſe intereſt viſibly it was (and alwayes will be) to pull them down; not knowing otherwiſe how to diſpoſe either of themſelves, or the power they had taken from the Protector, and the former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nay, are now content to have their officers thrown out after an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary manner, and thoſe that remain, forced to take Commiſſions from their new Maſters, and old enemies; which are to laſt but for a few moneths, and poſſibly be taken away before many dayes paſs over. In the mean time aw'd with the excluſion from indempnity, as alſo the raiſing County Troops, and new <hi>Militia's,</hi> which (what ever is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) are deſigned onely to check and curb them: likewiſe, the Arrears ſo pitifully ſatisfied, that they ſeem rather a jeer then payment; and yet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114608:4"/>they chuſe to ſubmit to all this, rather then venture the confuſion of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the power into their own hands.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The pretenſions of the <hi>Protectorian</hi> Intereſt, are now ſo lowe, ſo odious; and what is worſe then that, ridiculous to the Nation, the ſeveral Members of the Family, having been falſe to one another, and their beſt friends, and the late Heir, having in his perſon betrayed ſo much folly and cowardize, (two ingredients which will deſtroy any Government;) 'twould be impertinent to ſhew that it cannot be acquired, or if poſſibly returned, could not be ſetled; and of the unattainableneſſe of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, the old Protector himſelf would be further evidence, whoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and repute in the World, gave him advantages far before thoſe, any of his Line can hope to have; and yet we ſee, he could never get that title he ſo much thirſted for; and he had gained it (which it is credibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, he deſigned upon that very day he dyed) 'tis viſible to prudent men, how fatal it would have been, even to him: But laſtly, how far it would be from the Intereſt of the Nation, to eſpouſe ſuch a quarrell, as the maintenance of that Family with their lives and fortunes; let them be Judges, who in their Addreſſes ſolemnly promiſed to do ſo, and within few weeks after utterly deſerted it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The remnant <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Intereſt, is of like nature; that riſes meerly by the Armies favour, and can ſtand only on its Ruine, and the Nations. Its plea of right is ſo thin, that a ſober perſon would be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to own it; they being (to paſſe by other failances) long agoe, legally diſſolved in the death of the King: after apparently made unfree at leaſt, by the ſecluſion of their Members. Laſtly, actually diſſolved by the late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, which was acknowledged by as many Members againſt themſelves as ſate in intermediate Parliaments; eſpecially in the laſt, which was called upon the old national account, and had the authority of the Act, for a triennial Parliament to ground their convention: and now to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Tyranny and Uſurpation, this carcaſe of a Parliament, dead many yeers ago, being conjured up from its aſhes and rottenneſs, by the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Army, continues the old ſecluſion ſtill, and fills not up the vacant places: nay, is ſo far from filling up, that its primary aim is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the conſtitution of Parliaments; and though it pretends to popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, dares not refer it ſelf to the free votes of the people; nor may they hope to fool the Nation, with promiſes of not outſitting a prefixt time, or their <hi>Rotations</hi> and <hi>Fantaſtical Elections,</hi> which are no way grounded on the peoples choyce, and beſides lay no foundation of Settlement, as being unpracticable; and what is more, when ſetled, variable, both by their preſent Contrivers, and thoſe future perſons that ſhall be choſen; and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the Army, without whoſe licence nothing is valid, or of force: In ſhort, its pretenſions are far more deſtructive to the Nation, then even
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114608:5"/>the Protectorian are, it being better to ſubmit to the luſt, and ſerve the ends of one Family, then of twelve, or thirty, or what ever number the Olicharchy fixes. Its ſubſiſtence depending meerly upon this Army, whoſe viſible Intereſt it is to diſſolve them; they cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bring about their ends, for ſhould they take down this, and modell a new Army, the Intereſt of that would be the ſame, though the men were changed; and the mutual ruine of each other, muſt ſtill continue neceſſary for the ſupport of either.</p>
            <p>From which premiſes we may conclude; that the pretenſions of no party now on foot in the Nation are attainable: or if attain'd, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the good of other parts, or of the Nation; or in fine, their own: and from hence likewiſe, one would be apt to conclude, that the ruin of the publick is inevitable; there being no dore of hope left open to receive, no method viſible, to unite ſo diſtant and incompatible ends.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this, 'tis not impoſſible, no nor hard, to find an Expedient that ſhall evacuate all theſe difficulties: not only eſtabliſh the general Concernment, but (exorbitant paſſion only retrencht) ſatisfy the reall Intereſt of every party, nay ſingle perſon in the Nation.</p>
            <p>Now to the cheerful reception of ſuch an overture, I ſuppoſe there is no need to perſwade, nor more for to admoniſh, that words and names however rendered odious, are not to fright us from our certain benefit, and deereſt Intereſt. All that is demanded here, is, that if upon ſerious conſideration, the propoſal be found reaſonable, men would be ſo kind to themſelves as to receive it. The Aſſertion I doubt not to make moſt plain and evident, and therefore ſhal as plainly pronounce it. 'Tis this, <hi>The calling in the King, is the certain and only means for the preſervation of the Kingdome, and alſo of the rights and Intereſt, of all ſingle perſons in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make this evident in every part, I will retain the former Method, and take a juſt account of all the before mentioned particulars, that there may be no poſſibility left for Fallacy or Errour.</p>
            <p>I begin with the common national Intereſt, and that this accords with it, becomes manifeſt; for that the firſt requiſite, the eſtabliſhing the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws, neceſſarily brings in the King; this likewiſe affords a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal way for redreſſing of greivances of what kind ſoever, and a ſure and full Indempnity to all perſons; will ſettle Religion upon ſuch a Baſis, as ſhall give ſatisfaction to all that are for Government in the Church; as alſo thoſe that diſſent therein. It being viſible, that all <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> men are equally neer to him, to whom they relate not by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate names of Faction or Opinion, but by that one common bond of Alleigance; there being no more reaſon why he ſhould be partial in his affections to them, while they all agree in Loyalty, (though they differ in other matters;) than why a Father ſhould be fond to one Son, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114608:5"/>diſcourage another (both being equally obedient) upon pretence of their divers hairs or complexions, though Tyrants and Uſurpers have found it neceſſary ſtill to cajol and fool ſome one faction that they might make an intereſt which they had not, and by any means gain a colour and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to their uſurpation. This and this onely will advance trade, which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> quarrels have almoſt deſtroyed, will give an alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with neighbour States, his Family being already engraffed into the principal Stems of <hi>Europe,</hi> and his future marriage giving opportunity to make an advantagious affinity to ſtrengthen thoſe preſent intereſts; this will take off the vaſt charge of intelligence, and bribes hitherto employed meerly againſt the reſtitution of his Family: will ſuperceed the neceſſity of thoſe unreaſonable wars, that were begun upon that ſingle account, (I need not inſtance in particulars to make my ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.) 'Twill cut off the charge of the Appendages of this Crown, the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nations; which are now from hence become a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; beſides a ground of Everlaſting Jealouſie and danger. Yet further; the Government being put into the Kings hands, 'twill be eſtabliſhed not onely by that power which is committed to him; but by the more ſure exactors of obedience; affection, and duty. He being an hereditary Prince, his private intereſt muſt be the ſame with that of the Nation; which too will not be limited by the preſent age, but reach poſterity. This likewiſe very well con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s with the intereſt of all private parties, as anon ſhall be particularly made manifeſt: moreover, the Government will be put into the hands of a perſon, ſo fit for employment as no one living the like: his education through all hardſhips of fortune, his coverſe abroad in the Courts of the moſt conſiderable of his neighbour Princes; his managery of buſineſs in his own perſon, his engagements in warlike hazzards with others likewiſe of all kinds: his age perfectly mature, his underſtanding ſharp to apprehend; and reſolution ſteady to purſue: joyned with an infinite ſweetneſs of temper; concurring to make up ſo perfect a ſufficiency for Empire, that the moſt wanton wiſhes of men, cannot fancy any thing, that he wil not either make good, or out do. But farther, to manifeſt the reſtoring of his family to be the onely means of ſetling the Nation, I add this evident proof. That we have made trial of all other formes of Government, and of his in another Line, all in vain. Firſt of an <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> while the Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> ſurvived; then a <hi>Democracy,</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> by it ſelf: After, a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> in the old <hi>Protector</hi> and his <hi>Son:</hi> and now an <hi>Oligarchy,</hi> in the preſent uſurpers at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> ſo that there is nothing now left us, but either Anarchy or his reſtitution; beſides this, that the ancient regal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the deſire of the whole body of the Nation, becomes plain from hence, that all late Parliaments however unequally choſen, have,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114608:6"/>(or were ſuſpected to have) deſigned, the reduction of it; and that this is the preſent ſenſe of almoſt every man, is ſo notorious, that the late Petition of <hi>July</hi> 6. addreſs'd by the men of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to themſelves,<note place="margin">That themſelves penn'd that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, was at firſt eaſily conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known.</note> and for which they give themſelves ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn thanks, knows not how to diſſemble it, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes in plain terms, <hi>That the intereſt of the late Kings Son is cryed up and promoted daily, upon pretence that there will be nothing but confuſion and tyranny until he come to govern: and that ſuch as declare for a Common-wealth, are for Anarchy and Confuſion, and can never agree among themſelves what they would have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not farther inlarge upon this head, but proceed to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains before me; to juſtifie the Neceſſity of bringing in the King, in reference to the private concerns of every party in the Nation; and</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis the intereſt of the <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> for by that means the heavy payments now on their Eſtates, with other burthens, will be taken off: And as to the preſſures of Penal Laws, they cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how far from grievous they were in the late Kings time, the Catholicks living here notwithſtanding them, in more flouriſhing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than thoſe of <hi>France, Italy,</hi> or <hi>Spain</hi> did, under their reſpective Princes; and would do infinitely more under their natural King, than if any forraigner ſhould acquire the power by conqueſt: Beſides, they generally having adhered to the late King in his Wars, have no reaſon to diſtruſt the finding favourable treatment from his Son, and to ſhare that indulgence which he is ready to afford to even his greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Royalliſt</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant, beſides that, his principles ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege him cheerfully to pay his obedience where it is due, and look no further, is likewiſe by his intereſt concern'd to be content with ſuch a reſtitution of the King as allows no private reparations for paſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; they thereby acquiring full poſſeſſion of what remains; and the ſettlement of the Nation would make the ſmalleſt eſtate more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious than the greateſt would be, acquired by violence; which una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voydably would defeat all terms of union, and involve the Nation in new Wars: So likewiſe, if the neceſſary parts of their way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip be ſecured, (which no party would envy them, being in a manner gratified as much themſelves) other circumſtantial things, would be eaſily ſetled by a fair and amicable treaty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> intereſt this; as being the only way to preſerve himſelf from ruin at the hands of thoſe leſſer parties that have grown up under him; who utterly oppoſe all Government in the Church, the being and the ſupports of the Miniſterial function, and the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114608:6"/>of the Party in the State. The ſpeculative differences and conteſts with the Epiſcopal Divines, are in the opinion of moderate men of either judgement, eaſily attoned: And this complyance, as the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo will be the moſt honorable act to them imaginable; ſilencing all thoſe vehement ſuſpicions, and hard cenſures, that now paſs uncontroll'd; and juſtifying thoſe pretenſions of Loyalty to the King, which were wrote in their Banners, and ſolemnly covenanted for in the beginning of the War: Beſides, is upon the matter what was deſired at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> and agreed upon at the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi> But if any of the party be unſatisfied herein, let him conſult the late very memorable Writings of Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> which many have thought fit to deride, but no body ſeriouſly to confute, and he ſhall find what will abundn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly convince him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the Intereſt of the <hi>Baptized Churches,</hi> their pretenſions of throwing down all other parties, being not feizable; 'tis their concern to acquieſe in the moſt moderate Church-government, which is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Epiſcopal, confeſt to be ſuch, even as exerciſed heretofore, by all parties in their diſputes, and differences with each other; and yet is fairly capable of ſuch farther allays, as ſhall appear to be for the peace of the Church and Nation. Beſides, it being a fundamental with them of the Independant way, to admit liberty of Conſcience; they have no reaſon to be angry, if perſons of different Judgements proceed according to their principles: And this being indulged to them, with the aſſurance of enjoying their temporal poſſeſſions, there is nothing imaginable, which with reaſon they can deſire more. Their aery Satisfaction of taking down Tythes, being ſo far from yielding them any real advantage, that 'tis moſt viſible, all it will do muſt be this, to tranſlate their payments from the Clergy to State farmers. And by that time they have taſted the difference between the precarious collections, and allmoſt begging of a Miniſter, and the cruel exactions and gripes, of a Publicans iron hands, I dare promiſe for them, they will heartily unwiſh, all their unreaſonable, and ill grounded deſires in that behalf.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is the Intereſt of the Army to call in the King. For firſt, to be under a ſingle perſon, is ſo palpably their concern that there is ſcarce a common Soldier among them, who is not ſenſible of it: and if ſo, then evidently, it is better to be under him then any other; for thereby they cut off the neceſſity of perpetual Wars, and ſo the hazzarding of all their acquiſitions; thereby they aſſure themſelves, from thoſe dangers of being taken down, ſtopt in pay, and defeared of Arrears: He being the only perſon that can (with a free Parliament) raiſe Contributions and Taxes in a legal manner, and to the ſatisfaction of the Nation. And the only one that can truſt them as a ſtanding body, which uſurpers never muſt do, as is manifeſt by the treatment, the Army has hither to had under their ſeveral Maſters; for to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114608:7"/>paſſe by their preſent uſage, before decypher'd by me; The old Protector made them States and properties, not only to aſſiſt his Tyranny, employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them upon the Enemies of his particular, and not the Nations Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: But did it alſo to eaſe himſelf of ſuch of them, as had more honeſty, wit, or courage, then he thought fit for his purpoſes. Hence they were caſt upon the <hi>Iriſh, Scottiſh, Flanders, French, Jamaica</hi> Service, turned on Shipboard in the Fleets, garbled, diſcarded, or removed from place to place, ſeldome truſted long under the ſame Officers, nor ſuffered to communicate Councels, or meet at a general Rendezvouz. When on the other ſide, a Prince that has a juſt title to ſupport him, has no ground of ſuch ſuſpicions, but repoſing himſelf on the loyalty of his people, will honorably, and with affection, treat, all that in any employment ſerve him. And as to the perſon of the King, he has a natural and particular reſpect for this Army; however they have deſerved of him: admiring their valour and diſcipline, even when employed againſt him; I will give but one inſtance, which, though it may ſeem ſlight, is not ſo as to the point in hand. 'Tis this, In the late <hi>Flanders</hi> ſervice, upon the occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mention of the Armies behaviour, in the engagements with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> forces neer <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> the taking of the Towns, and ſome other Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of leſſer moment, he was obſerved ſtill to give ſuch an affectionate teſtimony to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gallantry, as was no way pleaſing to the leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearers, who lik'd to have nothing beſides themſelves commended. Thus did he frequently contend for their honour, that fought againſt his honor, and life to boot; and was their Champion, who were his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And indeed it would be infinitely ſtrange, that they, who ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally ſpent their blood by Sea and Land, to eſtabliſh an ungrateful Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; whoſe recompence for the greateſt merits, was only the objecting unto new and greater dangers; whoſe certaineſt pay was ſuſpicion, affront, and injury; then afterwards ſubmitted to his Son a perſon of no worth or credit, of whom this comparative commendation can only be given, that he is not ſo very a Brute as his Brother; and (to cloſe all) aſſumed the long forgotten dregs of a caſt Parliament, ſhould envy to themſelves, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and advantage of being commanded by a Prince, of known Integrity and Virtue; a Prince that loves them, even in deſpight of all their inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and (which is the higheſt endearment among Soldiers) a Prince of eminent perſonal Valour, which ſeveral of themſelves are witneſſe of, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially at <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Mardike,</hi> and if they pleaſed, might be in more and fairer inſtances. Laſtly a Prince, who is the only viſible expedient upon earth, to render at once, them and their poſterity, and the whole Nation happy. Were this directed to the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Infantry, thoſe venal Souls, that underſtand nothing, beſides pay and plunder; theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments from reaſon, national Intereſt and honor, would poſſibly be loſt:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114608:7"/>But to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, that ſtill has owned a publique Spirit, where every common man, knows to direct as well as to obey, and judge no leſſe then execute; to have propoſed the Truth, muſt be enough: nor will they fail to fix their thoughts upon it, or ſteer themſelves as prudence ſhall inſtruct.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as to the Intereſt of the Protectors party, and the Parliament, they are concerned to call in the King; for it being impoſſible for them, to make good their aims, it muſt be wiſdome to ſecure themſelves and their eſtates, and take part in that Oblivion and amneſty, which he is ready to give, as alſo thoſe rewards, which, whoever ſerve him in any kind, (eſpecially in being inſtrumental to his reſtitution) will be ſure to have.</p>
            <p>Now to all this, I can foreſee but one material objection, which is, that the ſeveral forementioned parties, can not be ſecured, that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the King will not be inſidious, and enſnaring to them; and that whatever engagements he now makes, when he comes to power he will in likely-hood reſcind and cancel. To which I breifly anſwer, that this is no real objection at all, for ſome body or other muſt be truſted ſtill, there being no living in the World without mutual confidence; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is inveſted with power, may do injuriouſly, in deſpight of any fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight: Beſides, amongſt all theſe parties, where each is exaſperated againſt the other, there will be the ſame or greater cauſe of Jealouſie, if any of them were ſuffered to prevail. And 'twould be worth the thinking of, whether it were not a manifeſt Judgement of God upon us, that broke the treaty with the late King, upon ſuggeſtions, that it was not ſafe to truſt him; and choſe to rely upon the faith of one of our fellow Subjects: That he ſhould prove the moſt perfidious perſon in the World, to all that truſted him; to the Parliament, the Army, the Nation, and even his private friends and allyes; inſomuch, that no hiſtory of any age or people, can yield a parallel to him for falſeneſſe, perjury, hypocriſie, and and breach of faith; and if this look like judgement, 'twill then be worth the weighing, whether it become us to go on in our infortunate infidel practiſe ſtill? In caſes of this kind, there are but two ways of aſſurance, I mean ſo perfectly incontroulable, as to be valid, if either of them both be preſent. The one is the honeſty of the perſon that engages, the other is his Intereſt; and here, not one of theſe alone is preſent: but both concur; which certainly muſt make up a ſecurity, beyond all doubt or queſtion. As to the Honeſty of the King, no malice has the impudence to blaſt it: his Moderation, Sobriety, and Juſtice, being as well known as his misfortunes are. Next, as to Intereſt, it viſibly concerns him, to be puctual in his engagements; Firſt, to offer pardon to all that ſtand in need of it, and then moſt faithfully to make it good, in each particular
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114608:8"/>loſſe of Credit, infallibly breaking the Merchant and private dealer, but ruining more irrepirably the publick national one; when on the other ſide, preciſe exact performance, ſtrangely ſupports both one and the other. Of the benefit hereof, I ſhall give an eminent inſtance of late memory in his own Family, and therefore of which we cannot ſuppoſe him igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. It is his Grandfather <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> who after long Wars coming to his right, beſides his relief from Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by no other humane aid, but the relenting and late wiſdome of his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and being forc'd to make a Peace, by many particular Treaties, ſtill was exact in keeping them; and received into his entire favour, and ſolid friendſhip, all thoſe who had fought againſt him; &amp; govern'd his moſt important affairs, both Civil and Military, by the counſel and conduct of his ſometimes Enemies, ſuch as were not onely the Duke of <hi>Novers, Villeroy,</hi> and Preſident <hi>Jeanin,</hi> but even the head of the League, the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> himſelf; to whom he committed the conduct of all the force of <hi>France,</hi> (though then perſonally preſent) when the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> came to relieve <hi>Amiens;</hi> and after, to make good his own promiſe of Indempnity protected him, being queſtioned for the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, by interpoſing his own ſupreme power when the chambers of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were ready to condemn him; though thereby he was ſure to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the imputation of reſcuing ſo great a Malefactor againſt the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the people, the regular proceſs of the Law, the paſſionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a diſconſolate Widow Queen, and his own particular neerneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the higheſt mark, his relation both in Blood and in Succeſſion. Yet by doing this, he not onely ſetled himſelf, but attained that greatneſs which no other method could have contrived for him. And why we ſhould think the King reſolv'd not to conſult as well for himſelf, as his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father did, I ſuppoſe it will puzzle the wiſeſt patrons of diſtruſt, to give the leaſt pretence or ſhew of reaſon; as alſo it would do, why We ſhould not take pattern by that part of the Story which as neerly concerns us; for they being exactly in the ſame caſe we now are in, crumbled into as many diviſions and ſubdiviſions, as ſo great variety of Intereſt and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in that long Civil war could make; bearing an inveterate mortal hatred each to other, and almoſt all of them to the King; yet ſeeing the ruine approaching, both from themſelves and ſtrangers, the whole <hi>French</hi> Nation did ſubmit to that Prince againſt, whoſe throat their ſword had ſo often pointed, and whom they had for ſo many years devoted to hell as well as death, under the title of Heritick and Apoſtate; and by ſo doing became ſuddenly the moſt flouriſhing and the moſt potent people of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> But beſides all this, the King has yet a farther motive to offer Grace to all that will accept it, and religiouſly to make it good, that is peculiar to himſelf, and of proportionate value with him; the command and ſtrict
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114608:8"/>injunction of his dying Father, whoſe memory he too much eſteems, not to fulfill that legacy and laſt bequeſt of his, were there no other motive to perſwade him. His ſcrupulouſneſs in this particular is known to be ſuch, as to become a charge againſt him, and that with more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary vehemence, from the hot-ſpurs of the two extreme parties he has had occaſion to deal with, the <hi>Catholick</hi> and the <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byterian.</hi> The injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I mean is notorious to every perſon, making up a great part of the Miſſive, directed to the now preſent King, under the ſtyle of Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Kings Book</hi> Sect. 27.</note> I cannot forbear to inſert a few lines as they fell from the Pen of the incomparable Author: They run thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>I have offered Acts of Indempnity and Oblivion in ſo great a latitude as may include all that can but ſuſpect themſelves to be any way obnoxious to the Laws; and which might ſerve to exclude all future jealouſies and inſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</p>
               <p>I would have you alwayes propenſe to the ſame way, when ever it ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and accepted, let it be granted, not onely as an act of State policy and niceſſity, but of Chriſtian charity and choyce.</p>
               <p>It is all I have now left me, a power to forgive thoſe that have depriv'd me of all; and I thank God I have a heart to do it, and joy as much in this grace which God has given me, as in all my former enjoyments; for this is a greater argument of God love to me, than any proſperity can be.</p>
               <p>Be confident, as I am, that the moſt of all ſides who have done amiſs, have done ſo, not out of malice, but miſinformation, or miſapprehenſion of things.</p>
               <p>None will be more loyal and faithful to me and you, than thoſe Subjects who ſenſible of their Errors and our Injuries, will feel in their own ſouls moſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment motives to repentance, and earneſt deſires to make ſome reparations for their former defects.</p>
            </q>
            <p>But, if all this be not enough to ſuperſede ſuſpicion and doubt, let me yet add a farther teſtimony. The King admits at this day to his boſome and neereſt truſt, ſeveral perſons, that have been engaged againſt his father, and ſome of them in actions moſt fatal to his affairs; an infallible aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that it is only the fault of the reſt, that they are not there too; more then this, concerning a future performance to aſſure it, can not be ſaid or done, except it ſhould pleaſe God to work Miracles, which I hope no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy does now expect.</p>
            <p>The ſhort of all is. Without truſting ſome one or other, the Nation is certainly deſtroyed, and no perfon in the World, beſides the King, is in a capacity to avert the impendent ruin, or can give the like ſecurity of himſelf, as he can do; I will not now preſcribe unto the Readers under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in dictating an inference; but from the Premiſes, deſire him at his leiſure to draw out the Concluſion.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114608:9"/>
            <p>Having thus without paſſion, partiality, or prejudice, endevoured clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to lay down the exact caſe of the Nation, both in reſpect of its diſeaſe and cure: 'twill be ſuperfluous to add perſwaſives; for men do not uſe to be importuned to leave their torment or diſeaſe, or want rhetorical En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, after the pleadings of Intereſt and Profit. I forbear therefore to addreſſe my ſelf unto affection, and to beg that thing, which viſibly it concerns them that are courted, to render their importunate requeſt and ſuit: Nor will I enlarge upon the Motives yet untoucht, drawn from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the reſpects of Proteſtations, Covenants, and Oaths; as alſo native allegiance, or what is infinitely conſiderable; Motives taken from the ſtate of publick affairs abroad; our neighbour Nations, being now at peace among themſelves, and looking out for forraign War, thereby to employ their uſeleſſe forces; pretence, and colour, and deſire too, for the undertaking of which, we have given to every one about us, in our late attempts on them; and likewiſe yeelds aſſurance, that they ſhall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by our diſagreement here among our ſelves. Let all this be ſeriouſly weigh'd: I am factor for no iutereſt or party, nor ſeek the thanks or favour of any derſon, but rather expect the fate of Reconcilers, to diſpleaſe every body: but let that ſucceed as it ſhall happen; the injury that I have done, cannot certainly be eſteemed great, all that is ſaid, amounting but to this very reaſonable deſire, that my fellow Subjects will remember theſe two plain truths, that they are <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and ſo conſider the good of the Nation; and then that they are Men, and ſo purſue their own.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
